<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akn:akomaNtoso xmlns:akn="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><akn:act name="statute"><akn:meta><akn:identification source="#legislature-ne"><akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ne/act/60/3,125" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ne/act/60/3,125" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#legislature-ne" /><akn:FRBRcountry value="us-ne" /><akn:FRBRnumber value="60-3,125" /></akn:FRBRWork><akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ne/act/60/3,125/eng@2025-12-31" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ne/act/60/3,125/eng@2025-12-31" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /><akn:FRBRlanguage language="eng" /></akn:FRBRExpression><akn:FRBRManifestation><akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-ne/act/60/3,125/eng@2025-12-31/akn.xml" /><akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-ne/act/60/3,125/eng@2025-12-31/akn.xml" /><akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="generation" /><akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" /></akn:FRBRManifestation></akn:identification><akn:publication date="2025-12-31" name="Nebraska Revised Statutes" showAs="Nebraska Revised Statutes" /><akn:references source="#legislature-ne"><akn:TLCOrganization eId="legislature-ne" href="https://nebraskalegislature.gov/" showAs="Nebraska Legislature" /><akn:TLCOrganization eId="cosilico" href="https://cosilico.ai/" showAs="Cosilico" /><akn:passiveRef eId="ref_0" href="/akn/us-ne/act/60/385" showAs="Section 60-385" /><akn:passiveRef eId="ref_1" href="/akn/us-ne/act/60/370" showAs="Section 60-370" /><akn:passiveRef eId="ref_2" href="/akn/us-ne/act/60/3,102" showAs="Section 60-3,102" /><akn:passiveRef eId="ref_3" href="/akn/us-ne/act/60/3,118" showAs="Section 60-3,118" /><akn:passiveRef eId="ref_4" href="/akn/us-ne/act/60/3,113" showAs="Section 60-3,113" /><akn:passiveRef eId="ref_5" href="/akn/us-ne/act/60/3,198" showAs="Section 60-3,198" /><akn:passiveRef eId="ref_6" href="/akn/us-ne/act/80/414" showAs="Section 80-414" /><akn:passiveRef eId="ref_7" href="/akn/us-ne/act/60/3,113.02" showAs="Section 60-3,113.02" /></akn:references><akn:notes source="#legislature-ne"><akn:note eId="source_0"><akn:p>Laws 2005, LB 274, § 125;</akn:p></akn:note><akn:note eId="source_1"><akn:p>Laws 2007, LB286, § 43;</akn:p></akn:note><akn:note eId="source_2"><akn:p>Laws 2009, LB110, § 10;</akn:p></akn:note><akn:note eId="source_3"><akn:p>Laws 2014, LB383, § 7;</akn:p></akn:note><akn:note eId="source_4"><akn:p>Laws 2017, LB263, § 47;</akn:p></akn:note><akn:note eId="source_5"><akn:p>Laws 2019, LB138, § 15;</akn:p></akn:note><akn:note eId="source_6"><akn:p>Laws 2019, LB270, § 21;</akn:p></akn:note><akn:note eId="source_7"><akn:p>Laws 2021, LB78, § 4;</akn:p></akn:note><akn:note eId="source_8"><akn:p>Laws 2022, LB750, § 25;</akn:p></akn:note><akn:note eId="source_9"><akn:p>Laws 2025, LB398, § 29.</akn:p></akn:note><akn:note eId="source_10"><akn:p>Operative Date: September 3, 2025</akn:p></akn:note></akn:notes></akn:meta><akn:body><akn:chapter eId="chp_60"><akn:num>60</akn:num><akn:section eId="sec_60-3_125"><akn:num>60-3,125</akn:num><akn:heading>Purple Heart plates; designs; eligibility; verification; fee.</akn:heading><akn:content><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_1">(1)(a)(i) Any person may, in addition to the application required by section60-385, apply to the department for license plates designed by the department to indicate that the applicant has received from the federal government an award of a Purple Heart. The inscription of the plates shall be designed so as to include a facsimile of the award and beneath any numerical designation upon the plates pursuant to section60-370the words Purple Heart separately on one line and the words Combat Wounded on the line below.</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_2">(ii)(A) Beginning January 1, 2026, one type of Purple Heart license plates shall be alphanumeric plates. No license plate fee shall be required for such license plates. The department shall:</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_3">(I) Assign a designation up to five characters; and</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_4">(II) Not use a county designation.</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_5">(B)(I) One type of Purple Heart license plates shall be personalized message license plates. Such license plates shall be issued subject to the same conditions specified for personalized message license plates in section60-3,118, except that a maximum of five characters may be used.</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_6">(II) Each application for initial issuance of personalized message Purple Heart license plates shall be accompanied by a fee of forty dollars. An application for renewal of such license plates shall be accompanied by a fee of forty dollars. Fees collected under this subdivision (1)(a)(ii)(B)(II) shall be remitted to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit twenty-five percent of such fee to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund and seventy-five percent of such fee to the Nebraska Veteran Cemetery System Operation Fund.</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_7">(III) No license plate fee under section60-3,102shall be required for personalized message Purple Heart license plates issued under this section, other than the fee provided for in subdivision (1)(a)(ii)(B)(II) of this section.</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_8">(b)(i) Beginning January 1, 2026, any person may, in addition to the application required by section60-385, apply to the department for license plates designed by the department to indicate that the applicant has received from the federal government an award of a Purple Heart. The inscription of the plates shall be designed so as to include a facsimile of the award and beneath any numerical designation upon the plates pursuant to section60-370the words Purple Heart separately on one line and the words Combat Wounded on the line below. Such license plates shall also carry the internationally accepted wheelchair symbol specified in section60-3,113.</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_9">(ii)(A) One type of Purple Heart license plates that carry the internationally accepted wheelchair symbol shall be alphanumeric plates. No license plate fee shall be required for such license plates. The department shall:</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_10">(I) Assign a designation up to three characters; and</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_11">(II) Not use a county designation.</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_12">(B)(I) Beginning January 1, 2026, one type of Purple Heart license plates that carry the internationally accepted wheelchair symbol shall be personalized message license plates. Such license plates shall be issued subject to the same conditions specified for personalized message license plates in section60-3,118, except that a maximum of three characters may be used.</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_13">(II) Each application for initial issuance of personalized message Purple Heart license plates that carry the internationally accepted wheelchair symbol shall be accompanied by a fee of forty dollars. An application for renewal of such license plates shall be accompanied by a fee of forty dollars. Fees collected under this subdivision (1)(b)(ii)(B)(II) shall be remitted to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit twenty-five percent of such fee to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund and seventy-five percent of such fee to the Nebraska Veteran Cemetery System Operation Fund.</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_14">(III) No license plate fee under section60-3,102shall be required for personalized message Purple Heart license plates issued under this section, other than the fee provided for in subdivision (1)(b)(ii)(B)(II) of this section.</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_15">(c) Beginning January 1, 2026, a trust that owns a motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer may apply for the license plates described in subdivision (1)(a) or (b) of this section if a designated beneficiary of the trust qualifies for such license plates.</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_16">(2)(a) To be eligible for license plates under this section, a person shall register with the Department of Veterans' Affairs pursuant to section80-414. The Department of Motor Vehicles shall verify an applicant's eligibility using the registry established by the Department of Veterans' Affairs pursuant to section80-414prior to issuing any license plates under this section.</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_17">(b) To be eligible for the license plates described in subdivision (1)(b) of this section, in addition to any other eligibility requirements for such license plates under this section:</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_18">(i) An application and proof of disability in the form and with the information required by section60-3,113.02shall be submitted before issuance or reissuance of such license plates; and</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_19">(ii) The handicap or disability of the handicapped or disabled person shall be certified as permanent.</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_20">(c) Any number of motor vehicles, trailers, or semitrailers owned by the applicant may be licensed under this section at any one time. Motor vehicles and trailers registered under section60-3,198shall not be so licensed.</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_21">(3) If license plates issued pursuant to this section are lost, stolen, or mutilated, the recipient of the plates shall be issued replacement license plates upon request and without charge.</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_22">(4) License plates issued under this section shall not require the payment of any additional license plate fees and shall be permanently attached to the vehicle to which the plates are registered as long as the vehicle is properly registered by the applicant annually.</akn:p><akn:p eId="sec_60-3_125__p_23">(5) The county treasurer or the department may issue temporary license stickers to the applicant under this section for the applicant to lawfully operate the vehicle pending receipt of the license plates. No charge in addition to the registration fee shall be made for the issuance of a temporary license sticker under this subsection. The department shall furnish temporary license stickers for issuance by the county treasurer at no cost to the counties. The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations regarding the design and issuance of temporary license stickers.</akn:p></akn:content></akn:section></akn:chapter></akn:body></akn:act></akn:akomaNtoso>